so hi my name is Jill brewer and in this
short video I want to share a
presentation that I've put together
explaining the larger vision for
creating culture design labs as a way of
helping humanity deal with the global
crisis so first off let me share that
right now it is currently not possible
to guide the evolution of social systems
in the world so we have political
systems economies communities urban
development processes technology design
and so on that are happening without any
ability to set collective actions around
shared intention and purpose and this is
a really serious problem for us because
of the number of friends that are
dominating the changes in the world that
take place at an exponential scale so
most of us are familiar with how quickly
technology is changing and that we can
have paradigm shifts and how we
communicate or the tools that we use
over a period of a few years but there
are other exponential processes that are
dominating in the world today and just
one example to give you a sense is
population growth if you look at the
trends in human population in the last
100 years it's been growing in an
exponential rate which is causing us to
have tremendous negative impacts on the
planet itself so these exponential
change processes are dominating in the
world and this is causing very powerful
forms of cultural evolution yet that
evolution is not happening in a
conscious or intentional manner so we
need to change this situation quite
desperately the reason we need to do
this is that the current trajectory for
our planetary system is overshoot and
collapse so we can see this with global
warming where we're moving into a realm
of runaway climate change if we continue
to increase the amount of fossil fuels
burned each year grow the human
population and
deplete more resources as we drive the
planet further and further into a motive
instability and disruption so this
trajectory you know whether we're
thinking about it in terms of the models
developed in the 1970s where the Club of
Rome or more recently by the Stockholm
resilience center where they have nine
planetary boundaries any of which
crossed in planetary civilization
becomes untenable currently according to
the best estimates we've crossed four of
those nine boundaries so what that means
is we're currently on a pathway to
catastrophic collapse at a planetary
scale and we need to learn how to guide
cultural evolution for our societies and
we need to do this very quickly one of
the things that gets in the way of doing
this is that the knowledge that we need
to apply to be able to guide the
evolution of our very complex societies
is mostly fragmented and silos at the
moment one place where you can really
see this as in universities or we've
organized our knowledge into academic
departments and disciplines where
biology and chemistry are is governed by
separate researchers and management
practices hiring practices admissions
for students and so on and so we have
this situation where our knowledge is
deeply fragmented yet all of our
effective interventions and solutions
need to be holistic and integrated so we
have to do design work on the process of
creating knowledge itself to help us
making a problem solvable and this is
what I call the predicament of knowledge
which has two parts one is that we are
making new knowledge at such a fast rate
that we can't keep up with it this is
one of the patterns of exponential
growth in the world today when we have
several million people getting PhDs
every year we're producing more
knowledge than we know how to handle and
it's coming more quickly than we can
possibly process so the predicament of
knowledge has two parts one is that
there's too much of it for us to handle
in any kind of reasonable ineffective
way and the other is that we're creating
new knowledge
fast-pace that our ability to guide
social learning to incorporate and
assimilate this knowledge into our
institutions and practices is greatly
mismatched we learn socially much more
slowly than we are currently producing
knowledge so this predicament is very
problematic because you know by the
assessments I've been doing seems like
we have all of the knowledge we need to
solve all of the major problems in the
world and yet is fragmented and it's not
being implemented or absorbed into our
institutions rapidly enough for us to do
so so we have this predicament of
knowledge that we need to deal with but
now let me give you a really inspiring
idea which is that every community on
earth whether it's a small village or a
mega city with millions of people is
potentially a field site for doing
research and applied cultural evolution
what I mean by this is that we can bring
the best integrative social sciences
together and create field sites for
monitoring and tracking social change
and all communities on earth now we can
create networks of them to help us learn
so as the world changes we're gonna find
that the ability to learn about how each
community is either adapted to its
environment or not will help us to learn
the skill of guiding cultural evolution
at large scales now of course some of
our communities are going to prove to be
resilient and adaptive in their
environments and there are going to
continue to grow flourish and thrive
into the future but that's not the case
for all communities there's one estimate
that really stands out to me which is
that in the Great Plains of the North
America in the United States 80% of the
cities and towns that have populations
of less than 50,000 people or going into
decline what this means is that we're
going to see many of these small to
medium sized towns disappear and go away
in the next 50 to 100 years so while
some communities are going to flourish
and thrive quite a few others are going
to die out and this is Darwinian
evolution in play where
the things that are well adapted to
their environments will remain fit and
be able to continue to exist whereas
those things that are not adapted to
their environment will die off and go
away now if we're talking about the
places that will become resilient what
we see is that there's a lot that's
already known about what makes a
community resilient and the picture I'm
showing here is of these sue backs and
the country of Bali and Sue backs are
these tiered form of Agriculture that
they use for growing rice and what's
amazing about the Sue backs is that
they're well adapted to their
environment that they're appropriately
diverse in the management practices for
how different farmers manage the land
and it's deeply integrated into the
political economic and spiritual
traditions of their culture and so
they're able to be self monitor ating
and this is a cultural tradition that
has lasted for a very long time so we
actually know quite a lot especially
from research by the historians and
anthropologists about how to create
resilient communities but what we don't
have right now is the ability to set up
monitoring and guiding of current
communities to have more of them become
so now I want to pause here for a moment
and draw attention to something that I
think is extremely important and that is
that right now we are leaving which
communities thrive and become resilient
and which communities collapse and go
away entirely up to chance so well this
is because we are not becoming active
managers of cultural evolution and what
I want to share with you is this idea
that life is too precious to be left to
chance so we need to be rigorous and
systematic about building an applied
science of cultural evolution for
communities around the world and this is
where we get to the idea of culture
design culture design as I like to
describe it is an integrative social
science that can help us dive the
evolution of entire communities so that
the individual people within them and
the entire communities become more
healthy and Rizzo
in a changing world and we need to do
this during a time when there are going
to be more disruptions disasters and
crises than we've ever had to deal with
in the history of our species
so with all of those exponential trends
driving change in the world we're gonna
see more hurricanes and tornadoes
wildfires we are going to see more air
erratic weather and unpredictability for
managing agriculture and food production
things like this that are going to
happen all over the world because of
global warming and the deterioration of
our environment and so during the very
time when all of that those disruptions
are happening or when we need to build
this field of culture design and create
networks of communities around the world
that are operating as field sites for
applied cultural evolution now in my
work to help build this capacity for
culture design labs around the world
I'm currently partnering with the Oregon
Research Institute in Eugene which is a
place that has a tradition for more than
60 years of building the field of Public
Health and applied behavioral science
and of course there's the cultural
evolution Society that I've been the
coordinator to help build which
currently has about 2,000 researchers
around the world in more than 50
countries who study cultural change from
a variety of different disciplinary
perspectives all of which are informed
by an evolutionary approach and then
there's the evolution Institute which is
a small nonprofit that coordinates the
bringing together of different kinds of
research and evolutionary studies both
biological and cultural evolution and
helps to translate that into materials
that are easily understood while also
doing things like the project that we
have to build the cultural evolution
Society which was a project incubated at
the evolution Institute and so I'm in
the process of building formal
relationships between these institutions
and other partners so that we can build
this capacity for guiding evolution at a
planetary scale so with that in mind I
say let's get together and play
we have very important work to do time
is short and this vision for creating
field sites for applied cultural
evolution in communities around the
world is needed more urgently than ever
before thank you and let's get to work